<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<chapter id="installation">
	<title>Installation</title>
	
	<para>
	This is the installation guide for the Scribble tools. Scribble is a notation for describing
	interaction based protocols between multiple parties.
	</para>
	
	<section>
		<title>Pre-Requisites</title>

		<para>
		The pre-requisites for the Scribble design time tools are:
		</para>
		
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
			Java
			
			<para>
			The design time tools are Java based, so you will need a suitable JVM (Java Virtual
			Machine) to run the tools. If you also intend to generate Java APIs, for use at
			runtime, then you will need a JDK (Java Development Kit).
			</para>
			
			<para>
			Download the version 1.6 (or higher) from the
			<ulink url="http://www.java.com">http://www.java.com</ulink>. Once
			downloaded, follow the instructions to install the JVM or JDK on your system.
			</para>
			</listitem>
			
			<listitem>
			Eclipse
			
			<para>
			The Scribble protocol descriptions can be edited using a standard text editor, and
			the Scribble tools can be invoked using command line tools (as described in the
			following chapter).
			</para>
			
			<para>
			However it is also possible to use the Scribble tools from within the Eclipse
			IDE environment, by installing the Scribble tools as plugins. If you wish to use
			this approach, then you will need a version of Eclipse (3.6 or higher) which can
			be downloaded from the Eclipse website:
			<ulink url="http://www.eclipse.org">http://www.eclipse.org</ulink>.
			</para>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
		
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Installing the Command Line Version</title>
		
		<para>
		To install the command line version of the Scribble tools:
		</para>
		
		<orderedlist>
			<listitem>
			Download the Scribble tools distribution from:
			<ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/scribble/downloads">http://www.jboss.org/scribble/downloads</ulink>.
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			Unpack the tool distribution in a suitable location
			</listitem>
			<listitem>
			Setup environment
			
			<para>
			The commands can be executed from the bin folder of the Scribble tools
			distribution. Alternatively, the <filename>bin</filename> folder can be
			added to the execution path, to enable the commands to be performed from
			any folder. 
			</para>
			
			<para>
			For example, on Linux running bash, simply edit the <filename>.bash_profile</filename>
			file within your home directory to add:
			</para>
			
			<informalexample>
				<programlisting>
				PATH=$PATH:${path-to-scribble}/bin
				</programlisting>
			</informalexample>
			</listitem>
		</orderedlist>
	</section>
	
	<section>
		<title>Installing the Eclipse Version</title>
		
		<para>
		The Eclipse plugins for the Scribble tools can be loaded from an update site
		using the update manager.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		Select the <emphasis>Help->Install New Software...</emphasis> menu item, from
		your Eclipse environment, and follow the instructions.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		If installing a stable or development milestone release of the tools, then
		the plugins can be installed directly from the network. If installing a nightly
		build of the plugins, to access the latest (but unstable) version of the tools,
		then it will be necessary to download the update site as an archive, and point
		the Eclipse update manager at the downloaded zip file.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		The location of the stable, development and nightly builds can be found on the
		Scribble download page:
		<ulink url="http://www.jboss.org/scribble/downloads">http://www.jboss.org/scribble/downloads</ulink>.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		Once the Eclipse environment has restarted, and if the distribution has been downloaded
		and expanded, then the next step is to import the samples into the Eclipse
		workspace.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		This can be done by selecting the <emphasis>Import->General->Existing Projects into Workspace</emphasis>
		and locating the <filename>samples</filename> folder from the Scribble
		distribution.
		</para>
		
		<para>
		This will display the set of projects within the <filename>samples</filename>
		folder, which can either be individually selected, or all imported at once.
		Once imported, the Scribble Protocol files can be opened by double clicking
		the file, to open the protocol context sensitive editor.
		</para>
	</section>
</chapter>
